Inventory of the Herbert H. Bateman Papers, 1946-1982, 1968-1982
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Letter and enclosures from American Cancer Society opposing the legalization of Laetrile in Virginia, December 1977., 4 items. (Box-folder 9:16)
  Series 97: Land Surveyors
- Correspondence and legislative papers regarding licensing of land surveyors, 1977, 1982., 7 items. (Box-folder 9:17)
  Including copies of 1982 bill regarding land surveyors and letters endorsing it.
  Series 98: Law Enforcement Training
- Law Enforcement Training, 1978-1979. (Box-folder 9:18-20)
  - Virginia Criminal Justice Training study, 1978-1979., 10 items. (Box-folder 9:18)
    Interim reports of August, September, and December 1978 and February 1979 report on police instructor certification by Diversified Management Research, Inc. Also contains Senate Joint Resolution mandating the study, agenda for initial meeting, and proposed membership list.
  - Reports and commentaries pertaining to Virginia Criminal Justice Study, 1979., 29 items. (Box-folder 9:19)
    Including February 1979 report on Virginia's Training Evaluation System and numerous letters, resolutions and copies of statements from officials of local and regional law enforcement agencies regarding training studies.
  - Reports and summaries from Virginia Criminal Justice Training Study, 1979., 8 items. (Box-folder 9:20)
    Including reports on pay, training, and education of law enforcement personnel, final summary for implementation of recommendations, and draft reports of advisory and steering committees on law enforcement training in Virginia.
  Series 99: League of Women Voters
- Position papers of League of Women Voters of Virginia on legislative issues for 1981, November 1980., 7 items. (Box-folder 9:21)
  Series 100: Leasehold Interest--Joint Subcommittee
- Correspondence, bills, transcripts of testimony and other materials relating to work of state senate subcommittee studying the taxation of leasehold interests, 1980., 13 items. (Box-folder 9:22)
  Series 101: Legislative Aides
- Resumes and letters of application for position as Bateman's legislative aide and payroll information on several aides including Thomas Carpenter, Robert A. Small, Mark Alan Stinson, Phillip Bruce Baker, and George Jeffrey Mason, 1977-1982., 52 items. (Box-folder 9:23)
  Series 102: Legislative Process
- Memoranda and articles regarding hiring of committee staffs and legislative reforms in other state governments, 1972, n.d., 4 items. (Box-folder 9:24)
  Series 103: Legislative Proposals, 1980-1982
- Legislative Proposals, 1980-1982. (Box 9-10)
  - Legislative Proposals, 1976., 20 items. (Box-folder 9:25)
    Carbon copies of Bateman's requests, January 1976, for the drafting of bills pertaining to a wide variety of issues.
  - Legislative proposals, 1980-1981., 28 items. (Box-folder 9:26)
    Correspondence, memoranda and bills relating to legislation proposed for consideration in 1980 and 1981 General Assembly session. File includes materials from Virginia Association of Counties, materials relating to regulation of barbers and hairdressers, material from Delegate Johnny Joannov regarding his bill to amend Virginia tax laws, and legislative agendas of Medical Society of Virginia and Virginia Poverty Law Center.
  - Legislative Proposals, 1982., 64 items. (Box-folder 9:27)
    Correspondence, memoranda, bills and legislative agendas from lobbying organizations relating to legislation proposed for 1982 General Assembly session, including materials from Association for Retarded Citizens, City of Newport News, Newport News Public Schools, York County Schools, Virginia Association of Community Action Agencies, Inc., League of Women Voters, and Riverside Hospital.
  - Legislative proposals - Bateman, 1982., 16 items. (Box-folder 9:28)
    Carbons and photocopies of Bateman's requests to legislative services [division] to draft bills on a variety of subjects for 1982 General Assembly session.
  - Legislative Proposals - Bills, 1982. (Box 9-10)
    - Copies of House bills and House and Senate Joint Resolutions introduced in 1982 General Assembly, and copies of several 1971 and 1979 bills, 1971-1982., 33 items. (Box-folder 9:29)
    - Copies of Senate bills introduced in the 1982 General Assembly session, 1982., 46 items. (Box-folder 9:30)
    - Copies of bills, amendments, substitutes and other materials related to progress of several House bills in the 1982 General Assembly session, 1982., 28 items. (Box-folder 10:1)
      Including appropriations bill, bill pertaining to motor vehicle insurance, transportation/highway funds allocation, and salaries of county court clerks.
  - Legislative Proposals - Reports, 1982. (Box-folder 10:2-3)
    - House documents for 1982 General Assembly session, 1982., 4 items. (Box-folder 10:2)
      Including reports on teacher preparation programs, fishing ladders along James River, and on feasibility of requiring thumbprints on drivers' licenses.
    - Senate documents for 1982 General Assembly session, 1982., 3 items. (Box-folder 10:3)
      Including reports on division of motor vehicles, mental health and feasibility of a new mental hospital.
  Series 104: Limitations on Spending
- Correspondence, bills and memoranda regarding 1980 proposal to amend state constitution to limit state spending, 1980., 18 items. (Box-folder 10:4)
  See also Proposition 13, series 154.
  Series 105: Litter Laws
- Litter Laws, 1974-1977. (Box-folder 10:5-7)
  - Copy of October 1974 report on the effectiveness and impact of the Oregon Minimum (Bottle) Deposit Law, and unrelated enclosed slips of paper announcing proposed changes on bear hunting regulations in Virginia, 1974., 10 items. (Box-folder 10:5)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports relating to General Assembly's consideration of deposit on non-returnable bottles, 1974-1976., 15 items. (Box-folder 10:6)
    Including materials from Virginia Beer Wholesaler's Association, R. J. Reynolds Aluminum, City of Lynchburg, and the Environmental Protection Agency, reports on litter control in Washington State and Virginia, copies of Assembly bills and Senate report, and floor speech [by Senator Waddell] denouncing Bateman's position.
  - Reports on Virginia's litter control plan and background reports on other states' litter laws, 1976-1977, n.d., 8 items. (Box-folder 10:7)
    Items include undated report (ca. 1976) of Senate subcommittee on container legislation on so-called "bottle bill" which figured in 1976 Assembly debates.
  Series 106: Lobbyists
- Rosters of Lobbyists registered by the Secretary of the Commonwealth for the Assembly sessions of 1977-1981, plus 1977 Virginia statute on lobbying, 1977-1981., 12 items. (Box-folder 10:8)
  Series 107: Local Revenue Sources
- Correspondence and position papers from Virginia Association of Counties, 1976-1978., 10 items. (Box-folder 10:9)
  Especially pertaining to the "severe fiscal dilemma" facing localities, and statistical tables on local source revenue data sent to members of House and Senate Finance Committees, July 1978.
  Series 108: Lottery
- Articles and assorted materials relating to Virginia's consideration of a state lottery, 1975-1979., 13 items. (Box-folder 10:10)
  Including winter 1975 issue of State Government featuring an article on lotteries, and letters and packets of information from Scientific Games Development Corporation sent to Bateman at beginning of 1978 and 1979 Assembly sessions.
  Series 109: Manufactured Housing Association
- Correspondence between Bateman, officials of Virginia Manufactured Housing Association, and Attorney General Andrew Miller and legal memoranda by Miller and by Bateman pertaining to zoning of double-wide mobile homes, 1972-1975., 39 items. (Box-folder 10:11)
  Items include legal memo prepared by Bateman for VMHA and material to YMHA's fund-raising efforts for Bateman's 1975 re-election campaign.
  Series 110: Marine Resources Management
- Marine Resources Management, 1969-1980. (Box-folder 10:12-13)
  - Miscellaneous reports regarding Virginia Marine Resources, 1969-1977., 9 items. (Box-folder 10:12)
    Including 1969 Times-Herald report on dangers to Chesapeake Bay, copies of 1974 agreement between Virginia Marine Resources Commission and Newport News Shipbuilding and Drydock Company, and 1977 JLARC report on marine resources management programs in Virginia.
  - Memoranda concerning 1979 Marine Resource Committee meeting, 1980 meeting of joint subcommittee studying pollution in the Poquoson and Black Rivers, and photocopy of undated college thesis on turn-of-the-century coastal resources (Baylor) survey, 1979-1980, n.d., 14 items. (Box-folder 10:13)
  Series 111: Medical Lien
- Correspondence and copies of bill relating to January 1980 proposal to require written requests ("Lien letters") from state or hospital in order to place lien on property of person(s) causing injury to others, 1980., 6 items. (Box-folder 10:14)
  Series 112: Medical Malpractice
- Medical Malpractice, 1975-1978. (Box 10-11)
  - Report on medical malpractice claims by National Association of Insurance Commissioners, plus an undated introduction, December 1975, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 10:15)
  - Report to the all-industry committee special malpractice review: 1974 closed claim survey preliminary analysis prepared by Insurance Services Office, 1 December 1975., 1 item. (Box-folder 10:16)
  - Background material on medical malpractice insurance "crisis," 1975., 12 items. (Box-folder 10:17)
    Including memorandum from May 1975 Medical Malpractice Conference, background articles, minutes of and statements before July 1975 meeting of Commission on the Costs and Administration of Health Care Services, copies of July 1975 draft legislation, and copy of September 1975 report on malpractice crisis by Virginia Hospital Association.
  - Correspondence, memoranda and legislative material relating to study of medical malpractice insurance crisis, 1975., 18 items. (Box-folder 10:18)
    Especially items pertaining to work of Senate Courts of Justice subcommittee studying medical malpractice insurance which Bateman chaired. File includes material on legislation or other states, especially the "Indiana Plan."
  - Bateman's letter of 19 March 1976 explaining provisions of bill (S. 115) passed-by Assembly, materials relating to Senate Joint Resolution, March 1976, to further study malpractice problem, and legal memoranda, June 1976, concerning challenge of constitutionality of S. 115, 1976., 20 items. (Box-folder 10:19)
  - Background information on medical malpractice insurance, 1974-1975., 14 items. (Box-folder 10:20)
    Including excerpts from federal report, May-June 1975 issue of Virginia Bar News, and unidentified packet of articles and memoranda (possibly from November 1975 conference in San Francisco).
  - Correspondence, reports and other material relating to medical malpractice issue, 1975-1976., 12 items. (Box-folder 10:21)
    Including November 1975 report of State Corporation Commission, statement by William Read Miller, attorney for the Medical Society of Virginia, and Bateman's handwritten notes from Conference of Insurance Legislators, November 1975.
  - Legislative materials relating to bills for limiting and regulating malpractice claims, 1976., 31 items. (Box-folder 10:22)
    Including copies of bills, amendments, substitutes, and roll call vote tallies, 2 February 1976 summary of legislation introduced, 12 March 1976 summary of action on two bills, statements by representatives of insurance and medical professions, and Bateman's correspondence with Attorney General's office and SCC Bureau of Insurance.
  - Correspondence and legislative material relating to medical malpractice insurance, 1976-1978., 19 items. (Box-folder 10:23)
    including undated acts, amendments and reports from 1976 Assembly session, approved copy of Act (S. 115), and letters of 1977 and 1978 discussing further proposals for amending malpractice insurance laws.
  - Letters received from constituents regarding medical malpractice issue, 19 January-9 February 1976, 77 items. (Box-folder 11:1)
  - Letters received from constituents, 10 February-March 1976, regarding medical malpractice insurance issue, and draft and sample copy (undated) of Bateman's form letter reply, 1976, n.d., 91 items. (Box-folder 11:2)
  Series 113: Medicaid and Health Issues
- Medicaid and Health Issues, 1970-1982. (Box-folder 11:3-4)
  - Correspondence and other materials relating to Health Legislation, 1970-1975., 58 items. (Box-folder 11:3)
    Including Bateman's position paper [ca. 1970] on state funding for abortion and constituent letters on this issue, copies of congressional bills and excerpts from Congressional Record on proposed "Radiation Health and Safety Act," 1970 and 1971, report on needs of the handicapped in Virginia, and 1972 legislative program of Virginia Hospital Association.
  - Correspondence, reports and memoranda relating to health care issues, including articles, statistics, reports and proposed legislation on health care costs, and long-term treatment, 1977-1982., 26 items. (Box-folder 11:4)
  Series 114: Medicaid Cost Containment
- Medicaid Cost Containment, 1980-1982. (Box-folder 11:5-8)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports, 1980., 27 items. (Box-folder 11:5)
    Mostly pertaining to state Medicaid deficit and cost containment options, including 7 September 1980 report by Virginia Health Care Association (VHCA) and 7 November 1980 rebuttal of it, cost containment option package, materials relating to 7 November 1980 meeting and several copies of VHCA November 1980 brochure on Medicaid and Virginia nursing homes.
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to Virginia's Medicaid deficit and cost containment plan, 1981-1982., 49 items. (Box-folder 11:6)
    Including correspondence from constituents, hospitals, and Virginia Poverty Law Center, Assembly agendas of Virginia Hospital Association (VHA), memoranda and statistical material relating to work of Medicaid subcommittee and meeting of 25 February 1982.
  - Briefing by Human Resources subcommittee, House Appropriations committee, and Health and Social Services committee of the Senate Finance committee entitled Medicaid - A Strategy for Containing Indigent Health Care Costs, 19 January 1982., 1 item. (Box-folder 11:7)
  - Memoranda, reports and correspondence, 1981-1982., 14 items. (Box-folder 11:8)
    Enclosed in January 1981 report by Commissioner of Virginia Health Department on nursing home bed need, and reports and memoranda on Medicaid from Virginia Health Care Association, Virginia Pharmaceutical Association, Virginia Optometric Association, and Hoffman-La Roche Inc.
  Series 115: Mental Health
- Assorted materials on treatment of mentally ill in Virginia, 1976-1978., 5 items. (Box-folder 11:9)
  Including 1976 report on treatment of children, December 1977 letter from Virginia Association for Retired Citizens, Inc., and 1978 article from American Bar Association Journal.
  Series 116: Metro
- Correspondence, memoranda, and legislative materials relating to financing of Washington Area Metro (Rapid Transit) System, 1976-1980., 23 items. (Box-folder 11:10)
  Including 1976 progress reports, copy of 1980 federal public law financing 801. of remaining construction, correspondence and statistical information from Fairfax County, [Virginia], officials and Assembly bills to allow taxation to finance remaining 20%.
  See also Transportation - Northern Virginia, series 200.
  Series 117: Milk Commission
- Milk Commission, 1973-1975. (Box-folder 11:11-12)
  - Background information on dairy industry and milk pricing policy for state Milk Commission, 1973., 7 items. (Box-folder 11:11)
    Including reports of USDA, Directory of Virginia Dairy Products Association, and history of Virginia State Dairyman's Association.
  - Materials relating to work of state Milk Commission, 1974-1975., 9 items. (Box-folder 11:12)
    including 1974 rules and regulation for milk industry, December 1975 final report of Commission to study Virginia Milk Commission, undated booklet, The Study of Milk, and 1978 memorandum from state Milk Commissions.
  Series 118: National Conference of State Legislatures, Urban Development Committee
- Material relating to Bateman's service on National Conference of State Legislatures (NCSL) Committee on Urban Development, 1978-1979., 32 items. (Box-folder 11:13)
  Including background on legislation and NCSL proposals, and agendas and minutes of and background information from several committee meetings.
  Series 119: Nature Conservancy
- Legislative materials relating to January 1980 state Senate bill to encourage state to buy lands and establish recreational facilities on Barrier Islands, 1979-1980., 8 items. (Box-folder 11:14)
  Including copy of relevant 1979 Congressional bill, copy of and comments on state Senate Bill 299, and newsletter of Outer Banks, [Virginia] Civic League.
  Series 120: Newport News Bar Association
- List of committee chairman assignments of Newport News Bar Association, with Bateman's appointment as chairman of Public Affairs Committee underscored, December 1979., 2 items. (Box-folder 11:15)
  Series 121: Newport News, City of
- City of Newport News, 1967-1982. (Box-folder 11:16-18)
  - Correspondence, resolutions and memoranda relating to City of Newport News, Virginia, 1967-1972., 48 items. (Box-folder 11:16)
    Items include resolutions by city officials, commentaries on pending legislation affecting the city, proposed changes in city charter, background information on taxation and planning in city and on Virginia Peninsula and Bateman's inquiries and action on behalf of city.
  - Material relating to City of Newport News, 1973-1979., 37 items. (Box-folder 11:17)
    Including city council resolutions on problems and pending legislation, planning commission commentary on proposed statewide building code, Port Authority statistics for 1972, information from Virginia Municipal League, and numerous memoranda, 1976-1979, from Progress Committee for Newport News.
  - January 1980 proposed changes to city charter, January 1982 resolution of city council regarding salaries for local detention programs and 1982 legislative agenda, 1980-1982., 7 items. (Box-folder 11:18)
  Series 122: Newport News Development
- Correspondence between Bateman and Governor John Dalton regarding assistance to Gloria Manufacturing Corporation, November 1980., 2 items. (Box-folder 11:19)
  Series 123: Newport News Downtown
- Correspondence and memoranda relating to formation and work of Newport News Progress Committee, 1975-1979., 54 items. (Box-folder 11:20)
  Series begins with minutes of September 1975 meeting at which city businessmen and shipyard officials noted decline in downtown business. Most of the file consists of agendas and minutes of committee meetings.
  See also Peninsula Economic Development Council, series 141.
  Series 124: Newport News Public Education
- Newport News Public Education, 1978-1982. (Box-folder 11:21-22)
  - Materials relating to legislative agendas Of Newport News schools, 1978-1980., 17 items. (Box-folder 11:21)
    Including agendas for 1979 and 1980, Bateman's notes on several meetings of school board and agenda of Virginia School Boards Association.
    See also School Distribution Formula, series 168; and Sex Education, series 180.
  - Materials relating to Newport News legislative program, 1982., 15 items. (Box-folder 11:22)
    Most items are from a packet of information provided by legislative liaison "Ned" Carr, and include statements on teachers' salaries and driver education.
  Series 125: Newport News Shipbuilding
- Newport News Shipbuilding, 1972-1981. (Box-folder 11:23-24)
  - Bateman's correspondence on behalf of Newport News Shipbuilding and Drydock Co. (NNS & DD Co.), 1972-1977., 70 items. (Box-folder 11:23)
    Items include Bateman's 1974 correspondence with Virginia Senators William Scott and Harry F. Byrd, Jr., lobbying for increased supply of steel to allow NNS & DO Co. build special fuel tankers for U.S. Merchant Marine, 1977 correspondence with Virginia's Congressional delegation lobbying for payment of outstanding government contracts to NNS & DO Co., and copies of replies and correspondence of Congressmen with other government officials.
  - Correspondence and reports relating to Newport News Shipbuilding and Drydock Co., (NNS & DO Co.), 1977-1981., 37 items. (Box-folder 11:24)
    Including Bateman's 1977 letter to President Jimmy Carter urging support of a bill requiring that at least 30% of U.S. oil imports be carried in American ships, testimony of NNS & DO Co. Board Chairman John P. Diesel, 1978 NNS & DO Co. report, A Decade of Progress, and undated memoranda and draft legislation regarding security at shipyard.
    See also Service Life Extension Program, series 178.
  Series 126: No-Fault Insurance
- No-Fault Insurance, 1971-1977. (Box-folder 11:25-26)
  - Correspondence, articles, and other materials relating to Virginia's consideration of no-fault automobile insurance laws, 1971-1976., 44 items. (Box-folder 11:25)
    Including 1971 packet of background information, letters and memoranda from lawyers' groups, letters from constituents and a copy (14 February 1973) of Bateman's form letter response, copy of bill and roll call voting tally for S. 300 (January 1975), and lobbying materials from several insurance agencies.
  - Background information on no-fault automobile insurance laws, 1976-1977., 9 items. (Box-folder 11:26)
    Including several issues of Trial Magazine and State Legislatures Magazine, commentary on no-fault legislation in other states, and commentary by Kemper Insurance Co.
  Series 127: Obenshain Campaign
- Correspondence, bulletins and questionnaires relating to Republican Nominee Richard Obenshain's 1978 campaign for the U.S. Senate, 1978., 13 items. (Box-folder 12:1)
  Series 128: Obscenity
- Obscenity, 1952-1978. (Box-folder 12:2-3)
  - Correspondence, ordinances, bills and court decisions regarding obscenity and pornography, 1956-1978., 23 items. (Box-folder 12:2)
    Items include 1974 and 1978 correspondence regarding obscenity laws, copies of 1974 Newport News laws, copies of 1974 Newport News obscenity ordinances, and photocopies of court decisions regarding obscenity, 1956-1964.
  - Photocopies of Newport News City Code sections, court decisions and Virginia code sections regarding obscenity, 1969-1972, n.d., 10 items. (Box-folder 12:3)
  Series 129: Occupational Safety
- Copy of special section of Virginia's Industrial Health and Safety Inspection Plan from (Newport News) Daily Press with cover letter, November 1978., 2 items. (Box-folder 12:4)
  Series 130: Occupational Therapists
- Correspondence, facts sheets and JLARC staff briefing regarding resulation and licensing of occupational therapists in Virginia, January 1982., 16 items. (Box-folder 12:5)
  Series 131: Oil Refinery
- Correspondence and memoranda on proposed petrochemical plant in Nansemond County, Virginia, 1973-1977., 17 items. (Box-folder 12:6)
  Including constituent correspondence (some with Bateman's reply), and memoranda on environmental impact of refinery.
  Series 132: Old Dominion University
- October 1981 memo from President of Old Dominion University explaining reasons for state paying 70% (instead of current 65%) of students' education, and February 1982 letters from O.D.U. students urging Bateman to vote against tuition increases, 1981-1982., 8 items. (Box-folder 12:7)
  Series 133: Operator's Licensing
- Bill restricting licensing of drivers under 18 years of age, January 1982., 1 item. Copy. (Box-folder 12:8)
  Series 134: Optometrist Legislation
- Optometrist Legislation, 1977-1979. (Box-folder 12:9-12)